<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xmlContent>
	<title>MegaWig RPG - Meta Games Within Games Role Playing System</title>

	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<text>MetaWig is a generic role-playing system that relies heavily on
			many of the concepts introduced in the Fudge/Fate game systems. In
			particular, the skill pyramid and Aspects are used almost as-is from
			those systems. MetaWig formalizes the concept of
			games-within-the-game as a way of resolving situations.</text>
		<text>MetaWig defines one primary game-within-the-game (we'll call
			them WIGs from now on), and that is called the Skill Challenge. It is
			an essential RPG game that virtually all RPGs define. In MetaWig,
			this WIG is played as follows:</text>
		<list>
			<item>First, the challenge must be described and defined, usually by
				the GM. Typical examples include breaking down a door, finding a
				trap, hiding unseen in a shadow, climbing a wall, noticing that the
				spider on the wall is of a deadly poisonous variety, etc</item>
			<item>A Target Number is determined, usually by the GM, a challenge
				that a 0-skilled character could accomplish a bit more than half of
				the time would
				have a target number of 11.</item>
			<item>The character trying to achieve success at the challenge rolls
				2d10 and totals them. If a Tool is used, it may provide bonuses
				(most likely not) to add to this sum. If the sum is equal to or
				greater than the Target Number, then success is achieved.</item>
		</list>
		<text>MetaWig defines several other WIGs that can be used at the
			discretion of the GM and players on a situational basis.</text>
		<text>There are three basic parts of a character in the MetaWig RPG:
		</text>
		<list>
			<item>Skills</item>
			<item>Aspects</item>
			<item>Tools</item>
		</list>
		<section>
			<title>Skills</title>
			<text>Characters have skills. Every skill is a word or phrase that
				represents said skill. It can be anything at all, provided GM and
				players agree the level of specificity is appropriate. Clearly, the
				skill "Doing Stuff" is too broad, but whatever the skill is, it is
				up to players and GM to determine what situations it may apply to.
				Skills also have a number value, indicating the degree of skill the
				character has.
			</text>
			<text>Skills are developed by characters in a pyramid. In order to
				have X skills at level Y, the character must have X+2 skills at
				level Y-1. In other words, their skills must form a two-sided
				pyramid beginning at 0. When a player "gains a level", they increase
				one skill by one point, provided this constraint is satisfied.
			</text>
			<text>The value of the skill for the character is usually added to
				the Challenge Roll.</text>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Aspects</title>
			<text>Aspects work almost exactly as they do in Fate. Characters will
				have a number of Aspects, which are words or phrases (just like
				Skills), but they have no value number. Instead, aspects can be
				invoked by the player at the cost of a fate token, or compelled by
				the DM, for a gain of a fate token. Uses of aspects include
				asserting story facts, gaining +2 on a challenge roll, or re-rolling
				a challenge roll.</text>
			<text>For more information, see the rules of Fate.</text>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Tools</title>
			<text>Tools are usually objects used to improve one's chances of
				succeeding at a challenge. A Tool is a word or phrase that indicates
				something the group recognizes as a Tool (ie, a sword, a lockpicking
				toolset, a rope, eyeglasses, etc). Tools have properties, which
				provide some guidelines for how they can affect challenges. The
				obvious property would be a challenge roll bonus. Other properties
				can be defined for Tools with an eye toward WIGs that the tool will
				be appropriate for. For instance, in a combat WIG, a sword is
				probably appropriate, and depending on how the combat WIG is
				defined, the sword may have additional properties defined relevant
				to combat. These properties are defined when the sword is brought
				into the game by the GM or player.</text>
			<text>If a character attempts to use a Tool in a WIG for which the
				tool's properties are not appropriate, new properties can be
				assigned to the tool based on the group's feelings about how the
				tool's current properties might tranlsate to a property for the
				unexpected WIG. For instance, should someone decide to try to pry
				open a chest with their sword, the sword becomes a tool in an
				unexpected WIG, in which case a challenge roll bonus number must be
				determined for the sword.</text>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Additional WIGs</title>
		<section>
			<title>The Graded Challenge</title>
			<text>Many challenges benefit from a sense of degree of success or
				failure, rather than a simple binary yes/no value. One could argue
				that any modestly significant challenge can benefit from knowing the
				degree to which the attempt succeeded or failed. For instance, take
				the challenge of climbing a wall: success can be achieved quickly,
				or only after a long time of exhausting effort. Failure can result
				in a stubbed toe or a fall from a great height.</text>
			<text>Additionally, some challenges are simply impossible to do
				without some sort of tool. No matter how good a thief is, how will
				he/she pick a lock without lock-picking tools? Some walls are simply
				not scalable without rope or claws of some sort. One could represent
				this by setting the Challenge Number to a value outside the range of
				2d10 and thus requiring some bonus from a tool to achieve the target
				number. However some challenges are impossible without tools, and
				extremely easy with them - this strategy is clumsy in trying to
				model the relationship between challenge difficulty and the use of
				tools. So, we define the Graded Challenge</text>
			<list>
				<item>Define the Challenge, as before</item>
				<item>A Target Number is determined. In addition a Challenge Grade
					is determined. This is also a number.</item>
				<item>The character trying to achieve success at the challenge rolls
					2d10 and totals them, applying applicable bonuses, and subtracts
					the Target Number. The result is the initial success level.</item>
				<item>The tool used in this challenge needs to define its multiplier
					value, which will be multiplied by the success level. It is assumed
					that the use of no tool has a multiplier of 1.</item>
				<item>
					Divide the multiplied result by the Challenge Grade and
					eliminate
					fractions. This is the success factor. They can be interpreted like
					so:
				</item>
					<list>
						<item>Barely successful</item>
						<item>Fair success</item>
						<item>Good Success</item>
						<item>Great Success</item>
					</list>

					<text>Or however is desired for the particular challenge.</text>
				<item>If desired, the degree of failure can be calculated in the
					same fashion, but take the negative value and apply it as above,
					but now greater negative factors mean worse levels of failure.
					Whether or not greater factors of failure are relevant is up to the
					GM or the challenge designer.
				</item>
			</list>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>A Somewhat Enhanced Graded Challenge</title>
			<text>This WIG is exactly like the Graded Challenge, with the
				exception that the tool can define a range of multiplier values. Ie,
				3 values, a LOW value, a MEDIUM value, and a HIGH value. When
				determining the tool's multiplier, roll 2d6. If two odd numbers are
				rolled, use the LOW multiplier value. If one odd and one even number
				are rolled, use the MEDIUM multiplier value, and if two even numbers
				are rolled, use the HIGH multiplier value. This is just a simple way
				of essentially rolling 2d2 and creating a mini-bell-curve value
				distribution. It has great effect when used for a gun in a special
				combat WIG, where a gun may graze and do very little damage, or it
				may strike the brain or heart and essentially do infinite damage.
			</text>
		</section>
	</section>
</xmlContent>